sentikinesis
サイミア
It is not allowed to hurt others with thymia.
情念動を使って
Every child in our mud whale
泥クジラの子供たちは
had been taught like this for long.
ずっと こう教えられていた
However,
けれど
we made up our minds to fight.
私たちは戦う決意をした
We had been training hard to protect ourselves
帝国の戦艦スキロスによる襲撃に備え
from the attack by the Empire's battleship, Skulax.
私たちが行なった訓練は
But the training was just like some unfamiliar role playing games.
不慣れなごっこ遊びのようだった
Nevertheless, they were the utmost we could do.
それでも私たちは精一杯で
And we were really serious.
真剣だった
Thymia does not act directly on human beings.
サイミアは人に直接働きかけることはできない
Therefore when we use its power,
私たちが力を使うときは
we have to focus the forces on bows, arrows and blades.
弓矢や刃物に力を集中させる
That's it! Think about the shape of the bow in your mind.
そうだ　弓の形を頭の中で思い浮かべる
Then image if you draw that bow.
ぐっと曲がるイメージだ
Also don't forget the arrow!
矢のことも忘れるなよ
I won't forget!
わちゅれない
Pull the string of the bow.
弓の弦を引っ張って
Then look at the mark.
それから的を見る
Look!
みゆ
Shoot the arrow over there.
あそこに矢が刺さる
Shoot!
たたる
Even the bows that are too tight for the children,
子供には引けないような弓も
they can draw with the help of thymia.
サイミアで補助すれば引くことができる
It also benefits the accuracy.
命中精度も上げられる
Moving the object itself
物そのものを動かすのが
is the basic usage of thymia.
サイミアの基本的な使い方だ
Hey you.
ちょっとあなた
Come here with us.
一緒に来てくれる？
What's up?
なんだよ急に
Shut up!
あんたは黙って！
Dark-natured guy!
ネクラ
Dark-natured baldy!
ネクラハゲ
What?
えっ？
Dark-natured record freak destroyer!
ネクラ記録魔デストロイヤー
No!
ヒイッ！
Let's go!
行くわよ
Uhh...
う〜
Hey, are you guys OK?
大丈夫か　おまえら
What's your purpose?
なんの用？
Bring them here.
持ってきて
Your clothes are torn, right?
あなたの服　破れてるでしょ？
Shinono felt sorry and told us to choose some clothes for you.
かわいそうだから見繕ってあげてってシノノさんが！
This color suits your skin!
あなたの肌にはこの色が似合うわ！
This one is also cute!
こっちもカワイイわよ！
I can't fight with them...
これじゃ戦えない…
May I trim it myself to make it fit me more?
動きやすいように縫い直していい？
Of course.
いいわよ
I will lend you the sewing tools.
お裁縫道具貸してあげる
My name's Urumi, glad to see you.
私はウルミ　よろしくね
Don't stay with those guys, they are not cool at all.
あんな冴えない奴らと一緒にいないで
Let's be together!
私たちと行動すればいいのに
Yeah!
ねえ
We are also confident with the performance of thymia.
私たち　サイミアの扱いにも自信があるんだ
Yep.
うん
Hey, tell us more about the enemies.
ねえ　敵のこと教えてよ
We want to fight together.
一緒に戦いたいの
...Because our...
…私たち…
...our friends were killed.
友達　殺されたの
Nobody knows whether the route we take is correct.
この道が正しいのか
But after 4 days, we will face the all-out attack from Skulax.
スキロスの総攻撃まで
Translator
字 幕 入 力
ssnake
ssnake
静寂よ　旋律よ　儚き印よ
静寂よ　旋律よ　儚き印よ
Timing
字 幕 編 集
zwc1991
zwc1991
砂上にこの地に　生き続けたのなら
砂上にこの地に　生き続けたのなら
罪を纏う世界から　鯨の歌を聴いた...
罪を纏う世界から　鯨の歌を聴いた…
運命を　感情を　抱くべき子たちよ
運命を　感情を　抱くべき子たちよ
さ  き
さ  き
その先へ　その未来へ
その先へ　その未来へ
導かれたのなら
導かれたのなら
幾千の声　空想の地へ
幾千の声　空想の地へ
舵を切って行こうとした
舵を切って行こうとした
バラード
バラード
幾千の声　砂の海の譚歌
幾千の声　砂の海の譚歌
That's Lasha-sama.
ラシャ様だ
We have seldom seen her recently.
久しぶりだ　見かけるの
But it wasn't that long since she joined the presbytery!
まだ長老会に入って間もないんでしょう？
It has been... 2 years?
確か…2年？
But she is already tottering.
でも　随分足取りがよろよろして…
Assign members of the vigilante group to each team,
各班に自警団のメンバーを割り振り
to train them.
訓練をさせて
And they should act together that day, so each team can be better protected.
当日は共に行動し　護衛も兼ねます
How about the members for that strategy?
例の作戦のメンバーは？
The problem is,
悩み所は
the shirushi loses their power of thymia
20代半ばになると大半の印は
after their mid-20s.
サイミアの力が落ちてくることね
We have no choice but make the children to fight...
子供たちに頑張ってもらうしかないんだけど…
Children...
子供か…
I will try find some people.
私が何人か当たってみます
Lasha-sama...
ラシャ様…
Do you feel good now?
お体はもうよろしいんですか？
It's nothing about my feelings.
私の体なんてどうでもいいさ
You were training the children, right?
子供たちが訓練をしていたね
Ye..yes...
え　ええ…
The new chief.
新首長
I've heard that your younger sister was killed by them.
お前　妹を彼らに殺されたんだって？
You must hate the guys outside.
外の連中が憎いだろうね
But you should never forget,
だけど　このことを忘れちゃいけないよ
the children may kill somebody tomorrow,
子供たちは明日人を殺してしまうかもしれない
the children may die tomorrow,
明日死んでしまうかもしれない
decided by you.
それを「お前」が決めたんだ
Lasha-sama,
ラシャ様
Suo cares about the children more than anyone else!
スオウは誰よりも
Kuchiba,
クチバ
what about you?
お前はどうなんだい？
You were together with Taisha,
タイシャと一緒にいたというのに
but you failed to protect her.
彼女を守れなかったから
Don't you want a revenge?
弔い合戦でもするつもりかい？
But you won't fight at all.
だけどお前は戦えやしない
The children of shirushi die for you.
犠牲になるのは印の子供たちなんだよ
Kuchiba!
クチバさん！
It's you presbytery's fault!
あなたたち長老会は
You only made us to suicide together!
集団自決という答えしか出せなかったじゃないか！
If you have complaints...
文句があるなら…
I don't.
いいよ
Do whatever you like.
好きにすればいい
Anyway, everything will come to an end soon.
どうせすぐに何もかも終わるんだ
And finally, the cursed children of the whale can be saved.
呪われたクジラの子らも
Lasha-sama.
ラシャ様
We can only wait for the death if we do nothing.
なにもしなければ死を待つだけです
We can't stop here and wait to die!
私たちは立ち止まるわけにはいかないんです！
Oni.
オウニ
You were selected for the strategy of the chief, right?
首長の作戦のメンバーに選ばれたの？
It's really dangerous.
危ない任務なんでしょ？
I'll bring something to eat.
…なんか食べ物持って来る
Jiki, let's go.
ジキ　ついてきて
Oni suddenly appeared in a corner of the residential area someday.
オウニは　ある時から
No one knows who is his parents.
誰が親なのか　誰も知らない
And he didn't belong to any team.
どの班にも属していなかった
That guy is always alone.
あいつ　いつも一人だな
I think he's name is Oni.
オウニっていうんだって
He's weird. Leave him alone.
変な奴　放っておこうぜ
Hey dude.
おい　お前
I'll let you be my underling!
おれの子分にしてやろうか？
I mean let's play together!
一緒に遊んでやるって言ってんだよ
Hey!
おい！
Ah!
あっ！
You dare!
てんめぇ～！
Eh...
あっ…
You idiot!
この！
Both of you violated the rule.
規則違反ですよ　二人とも
Cuz this guy hit my face.
だってこいつが…俺の顔殴った
I even bothered to ask him be my underling,
せっかく子分に
but he's cheeky...
生意気なこと…
You have to live together in the internal for a few days.
暫く　二人で一緒に体内で過ごしなさい
It's a chance for you to talk with each other.
ちゃんと話し合うようにね
Damn, I hate it!
ちくしょ〜　やだよぉ
Let me out!
出せよぉ
Why you want to be out that much?
そんなに出たいのか？
They're the same, here and outside.
ここも外も同じなのに
It can never be the same!
同じじゃねえよ
You don't feel bad in such a small place?
お前こんなせまいところ平気なのかよ
The island itself is small.
この島だってせまい
We are surrounded by the sand, can't make a single move.
砂にかこまれて　ずっと身動きできずに
We become adults and die, with ourselves cooped up in the island.
とじこめられたまま大人になって死ぬ
They're the same.
おんなじだ
Then... Then why don't you go out!
でっ…出ればいいじゃねえか
You scum scum scum!
このウジウジうじムシっ！
Get out of the island if you don't like it!
嫌なら出ろよ　この島を！
If you mean you can't go out,
おまえができないっていうんなら
I'll bring you out!
おれがつれてってやる！
Umm, that's it!
ん…そうだ
I decided!
きめた
You should be my underling!
やっぱりおれの子分になれ！
Ah no, be my heeler.
じゃなくて…手下になれ
But, this is also the same...
…だと　これもおんなじか
I get it!
そうだ
Be my fellow!
「仲間」になれ！
Then I'll bring you out!
そうすればおまえを外へつれ出してやる！
Hey you two, get out.
おう　二人共出ろ
You must hate to be sent to the internal.
体内送りは嫌だろう
Learn from it, and never...
これに懲りたらもう二度と…
But, it isn't that bad sometimes.
まあ　たまには悪かねえよ
Right?
なっ
Nibi, what will you do?
ニビ　お前はどうする？
Are you going to fight?
戦うのか？
I haven't given up my dream of going outside.
俺は外の世界に行くことをあきらめてねえんだ
I'll knock down every guy on that way,
邪魔するやつはぶっ倒して
and bring you out!
おまえを外へ連れて行く
Don't forget I was the leader at the beginning!
最初は俺がリーダーだったんだ
Yes you were.
そうだな
I still think so.
俺は今でもそう思ってるぞ
Cuz I'm one year older than you!
俺のがいっこ年上だし
Stop laughing!
笑うな
It was fun.
楽しかったな
But...
でも…
We can never meet them again.
もう　あいつらには二度と会えない
Stop crying.
泣くな
I can't!
できねえよ！
I'm not as iron-minded as you.
俺　おまえみたいに強くねえんだ
You are really amazing.
おまえはすごいよ…
I've never seen you cry, for even a single time.
オウニが泣いたところ　一回も見たことねえもんな
Oni.
オウニ
I... am a bit scaring.
俺…いつもちょっと怖かった
I don't know where are you looking at,
おまえがどこ見てるか分からなくて
and I don't know if you may leave us
いつか勝手に俺たちを置いて一人で…
and go somewhere yourself...
どっか行っちまうんじゃないかって…
I won't.
行かねえよ
Tell me with your eyes on me!
こっち見て言ってくれよ
Oni!
オウニ
Chakuro.
チャクロ…
Lykos.
リコス
You've changed clothes? It suits you.
着替えたの？　似合ってるよ
Hmm?
ん？
Take this.
これ
Because your clothes are worn-out...
あなたの服　ボロボロだから…
I sewed it with the old clothes they gave me.
もらった古着を縫い直したの
You did it? For me?
リコスが？俺に？
You don't need to wear if you don't like it.
…いやだったら着なくていい
Ah... Lykos?
あ… リコス？
After all...
やっぱり…
The minds... are annoying.
心なんか…邪魔だ
What are you doing here?
何してるの？
We are gathering the sand.
おちゅな集めてるの
Cuz it's Sunamodori tomorrow.
明日　スナモドリの日だから
We have finished 80% of the barricades on the east side.
東側のバリケードは8割方完成
Although the west side is behind our schedule...
西側が遅れてはいるが…
Suo?
スオウ？
It is impossible...
無理ですよね…
No,
いや
If we assign those who without any works there,
手すきの者を回せば…
Sunamodori
スナモドリ
The Sunamodori on the west side...
西側のスナモドリ…
What!
はあ？
At the moment facing the enemies,
奴らが来るってときに
how dare you think about playing with sands!
砂かけごっこしてる場合か？ああ？
But...
だって…
The children should have been looking forward that...
ちびっ子たちは楽しみにしてただろうけど…
But it is impossible anyway~
さすがに無理よね〜
More importantly, we have an assembly tomorrow.
それより明日は全体集会よ
You must make up our minds in concert.
みんなの心を　ひとつにしなきゃね
C'mon, chief-sama.
頼むぞ　首長さま
...Make sure you understand your position and role,
…それぞれの持ち場と役割をしっかり確認して
and prepare for anything that may happen.
事態に備えてください
This is the tactics for tomorrow.
以上が明日の作戦です
There may be something horrible.
恐ろしいこともあるでしょう
There may be something sad.
悲しいこともあるでしょう
But I wish,
けれども
through the sky and the sea of sand,
この空と砂の海を通して
our minds will always connect with each other.
私たちの心はいつも　ずっと繋がっています
When you are despaired and frightened,
絶望に蝕まれ　恐怖にさいなまれたときは
please remember my wish.
この祈りを忘れないで
I wish we shall always be together,
あなたたちに繋がる全ての命が
with you and all the livings connected with you!
いつも共にあらんことを
Suo-sama!
スオウさま…！
He has done well this time.
今回は上出来だな
It was splendid!
立派でした
Ah...
あ…
Over there!
あそこ！
We completed it with over a year, just for this day!
この日のために一年かけて完成させた
It's a masterpiece of our workshop!
工房苦心の大傑作
Automatic sand-splashing machine.
自動砂かけマシン
And the name is...
名づけて…
Automatic! Sand-splashing! Machine!
自動！砂かけ！マシン！
Nothing changed at all.
変わってないだろ
Maybe...
私が…
You thought whatever you do, I won't get angry at all.
なにをしても怒らないと思っているんですか…
You guys!
こら〜！
Nezu! Lo! Chakuro!
ネズ！ロウ！チャクロ！
He is more angry than we thought.
思ったより怒ってるぞ
Get down!
降りてきなさい！
No problem,
大丈夫だ
Suo is super bad at sports, we can definitely run away.
スオウは超運動オンチだし　逃げ切れる
I did get angry!
私だって怒るんですからね！
Push it!
押せ
Wait!
お待ちなさい！
Suo-sama has splashed sand!
スオウさまがお砂かけたよ
It's Sunamodori!
スナモドリだ！
Hey... Wait!
お…おい！
Suo, stop them!
スオウ　やめさせろ
Huh?
え？
Enjoy it!
無礼講！
The Sunamodori is an event held once a year.
スナモドリは
takes part in the battle and splashes sand onto others
泥クジラの民が全員参加する砂かけ合戦が
until the sunset.
日暮れまで行われるのだ
And there is another meaning for the Sunamodori.
そして　スナモドリにはもう一つの意味があった
The souls melted in the sand will come back to us
砂に溶けていた魂が　かけられた砂を通して
through the splashed sand.
私たちの元へ戻ってくるのだ
Sami...
サミ…
Sorry I'm smiling so soon after you die.
君がいなくなって何日も経っていないのに
But I have never forgotten you.
けれど　忘れたことはないよ
I will remember you ever and forever.
これからもずっと覚えている
Please keep watching me.
そばで見守っていて
What's up, Sienna?
何だい？　シエナ
You...
あなた…
I have to take part in the battle.
ボクも戦いに参加することになったよ
The presbytery has ordered me.
長老会から命令がきた
Please prepare for your suicide.
自決の用意をしておきなさい
I don't want your dead body to be ugly.
死体が醜いのはいけない
Does your heart feel nothing?
あなたの心は何も感じないの？
Hmm?
ん？
You cares only about whether the death of your wife is ugly?
気になるのは妻の死に方が醜いかどうかだけ？
The feelings of people
…人の気持ちなんて
can never be shaped and visible.
形になって見えるものじゃないだろう？
Why you cares about the heart
なぜ誰にも分からない心の在り方に
that nobody really knows?
キミはこだわるんだ？
Neli?
ネリ？
Thank goodness, you are all right.
よかった　無事だったんだね
I wonder after those happened to Fallaina...
ファレナのあと　どうして…
You are not Neli?
…ネリじゃない…？
Who are you?
君は誰？
Where is Neli?
ネリはどこにいるの？
That girl has returned to Mom's tummy.
あの子はママのおなかに帰ったわ
To heal Mom's wounds.
ママの傷を癒やすために
Mom?
ママ？
What is Mom...
ママって…
You can hear my voice clearly?
あたしの声　ちゃんと聞こえてるのね
Great!
よかった
I haven't talked with people for a long time.
ひさしぶりに人と話したんだもの
Neli and I are twin. We share the same blood.
あたしネ　ネリと血を分けた双子なの
αίμα
αίμα
Call me Emma.
「エマ」って呼んで
Emma?
エマ…？
That's right, Mr. Recording clerk.
そうよ　記録係さん
Hey, promise me.
ねえ　約束してほしいのよ
Wha... What? Promise?
わっ　な…なに？　約束？
Protect the island at any cost.
絶対にこの島を守って
You said you'll protect everybody in the underground.
地下でみんなを守るって言ったわよね
Forever... Let's live together forever!
ずうっと…永遠にみんなで一緒に生きていきましょうよ
I promise
約束よ
if you can survive,
あんたが生き残ることができたら
φάλαινα
φάλαινα
I will tell you all the secrets of Fallaina!
ファレナの秘密を全部教えてあげるわ
You mean the history of the mud whale?
泥クジラの歴史ってこと？
You know it?
君はそれを知っているの？
Emma, who are you and Neli?
エマ！　君とネリは何者なの？
What are you trying to tell me?
俺に何を伝えようとしてるんだよ！
July 17, 93 S.S.
砂刑暦93年　7月17日
Confirmed a fog caused by the sand dust, before dawn.
夜明け前に　舞い上がった砂塵による霧を確認
After the sunrise, there was a sandstorm on the sea.
日の出の後　海は砂嵐となり
And the visibility was completely obstructed on the sea.
海上の視界はいっそう遮られていた
We mud whale will intercept the enemies!
泥クジラはこれから敵を迎え撃ちます
The most important thing is,
一番重要なのは
to protect yourselves from the attacks by the enemies.
襲ってくる敵から自分たちの命を守ること
Hold back the enemies as long as possible, fight them back if possible.
できるだけ長く敵を食い止め　撃退し
Our goal is to survive.
生き残ることが目的です
And another thing for you.
そしてもう一つ
While we are in defense,
私たちが防戦をしている間
I ask you to penetrate into the emenies' battleship.
皆さんには　敵の戦艦に潜入してもらいます
And destroy Nous the Skulax inside the ship.
そして　艦内のヌース･スキロスを破壊し
Sink their ship.
船を沈めてもらいます
It's a very dangerous task.
この任務には大変な危険を伴います
Therefore I only gathered those who with high ability of thymia.
なので　サイミアの能力の高い人に集まってもらいました
They are the charms I made.
これは私が編んだお守りです
They were used for stuffs like hunting, praying for safety.
普段は狩りなどの安全を祈るためのものですが
Anyway please get it.
身につけていってください
Please come back safely.
無事に帰ってきてください
Yes, Suo-sama...
はい　スオウさま…
Good girl, that's a good reply!
よしよし　いい返事だね
Thanks.
ありがとう
Be careful.
気をつけてね
I don't need it.
いらん
But...
でも…
Shut up.
しつこい
This is not good. Have it!
いけませんよ　おつけなさい
I'm the captain of Team 3 of vigilante group. My name is Tokusa.
私は自警団第3班班長　トクサ
And I'm the captain of this assault team.
この突撃隊の隊長です
Let's cooperate together and respect each other!
輪を乱さず　協力し合いましょう
Oni-kun!
オウニくん
Thank you, Tokusa.
お願いしますね　トクサさん
Don't say that, Suo-sama.
いやだなあ　スオウさま
Aren't we friends! Trust me please!
僕ら友達じゃありませんか　信頼してください
Yes...
はい…
Lykos,
リコス
you are already a member of the mud whale.
あなたは　もう泥クジラの民です
Care more about yourself.
自分を大切に
Please be sure to survive and come back!
必ず生きて帰ってきてくださいね
Yes.
はい
Good girl, a good reply!
よしよし　いい返事
Chakuro,
チャクロ
since you're the only ones who have seen the Nous...
ヌースを見ているあなたには　どうしても…
Don't worry, Suo.
心配しないで　スオウ
Leave it to us!
俺たちに任せて
Thank you, Chakuro.
ありがとう　チャクロ
When you finished the loading,
荷を積み終えたら
board on the ship in order and wait for the next instruction!
順次笹舟に乗って　待機するように！
I'll go with you!
俺も行く！
Nibi, you are not elected.
ニビ　お前は選ばれてない
Remain here and protect Kicha and others.
残って　キチャたちを守れ
I've had enough! Don't leave me alone!
いやだね　おいてけぼりはたくさんだ
Nibi-kun, thank you for your willing but...
ニビくん　志願はありがたいけど　もう…
Shut up! Don't talk to me, you idiot vigilante!
うっせえ！　クソ自警団は黙ってろ！
Calm down.
落ち着いて
Hey, haven't you heard anything?
ねえ　何か聞こえません？
There are sounds other than the sandstorm.
砂嵐以外の音がするんです
What?
何？
They are coming...
…来てる
The enemies, they are right there!
敵は…すぐそこにいる！
乾いた海の跡　望んで
乾いた海の跡　望んで
まだ見ぬ対岸を描く
まだ見ぬ対岸を描く
囚われの心のままなら
囚われの心のままなら
こんな傷みも知らずにいた
こんな傷みも知らずにいた
美しい詞を告げたひと
美しい詞を告げたひと
夜明けも待たずに
夜明けも待たずに
果てのその先を泳ぐ
果てのその先を泳ぐ
虫の唄
虫の唄
眠らず君と聞いた記憶
眠らず君と聞いた記憶
手を　ただ結んで
手を　ただ結んで
半色でも　遠い国でも
半色でも　遠い国でも
短い一章に生まれた夢を
短い一章に生まれた夢を
抱きしめに行こう
抱きしめに行こう